Good evening everyone.
Welcome to the first listening session
for the medical psilocybin program.
Thank you for being here this evening.
By registering and joining this virtual
setting, you are agreeing to be recorded
and for the recording to be public. If
you do not agree, you may log off the
meeting at this time. I am Dr. Dominic
Zerlo and I am the director for the New
Mexico Department of Health Center for
Medical Cannabis and Psilocybin.
Joining me today from the department is
Brenda Martinez, the deputy director for
our center, as well as Rosalie Nava, our
health education program manager. We
also have joining us Carmen Batista,
Katie Fry, and Adrien Estrada, who are
our health education team for the Center
for Medical Cannabis and Psilocybin.
Also joining us to help with technical
issues and with ensuring that we stay on
track and on time is Kathy Ojiri, our IT
project manager.
As a brief update update for the
program, as I am sure all of you know,
Senate Bill 219, the medical psilocybin
act was passed by the New Mexico State
Legislature and signed into law by
Governor Luhan Gisham this past spring.
The statute took effect on June 20th,
2025 and requires the Department of
Health to stand up the program by
December 31st, 2027.
Currently, the program is working with
both the office of the governor and the
office of the secretary to assemble the
medical psilocybin advisory board.
This process should result in the board
being seated in September as has been
previously announced. Once it is seated,
there will be several additional public
meetings and listening sessions
scheduled. Some of these will be
conducted in person and some will be
virtual or hybrid.
The initial and primary purpose for the
board is to create, review, and
recommend rules, regulations, and
protocols for the structure and
management of the medical psilocybin
program to the secretary of health. With
this in mind, please remember that
specifics such as what lensures will be
required to refer or certify patients,
types of training and educational
curriculum which will be needed,
requirements for cultivators and
protocols for treatment have not yet
been determined.
This listening session and future
listening sessions are one way for the
board members and the program to hear
ideas, thoughts, and concerns from the
different community members who are or
who may be involved in the program.
As a reminder, this is being recorded
and the recordings will be made public
on the program website and please see uh
the chat for the link to the program
website as well as the slide being shown
at this time.
One exception to this and we do ask for
your help with regard to this is please
remember to refrain from using profanity
or inappropriate language.
Uh so that because this is going to be
online and available to the public, we
want to ensure that individuals who may
be under the age of 18 and may watch
this recording in the future are not
exposed to inappropriate language.
If there is inappropriate language, it
may result in the recording not being
made available to the public, but would
still be available upon request.
As we start this the listening session
portion of this evening, in order to
speak, please raise your hand. If you
are on a computer, you can use the hand
icon near the top of the team's window
and it says raise under the icon and in
the image being shown, it is circled by
the yellow box on the image. If you are
on the team's app on a phone, please
press the ellipses, the three dots in
the menu, and then the hand icon will
appear and you can select it. If you are
joining on phone and through voice only,
you can press star five to raise or
lower your hand. And just as a note,
once uh you are uh you are called to
speak, you will be unmuted from the from
the listening session and you will be
able to then unmute yourself or mute
yourself as you would like. And to do
so, please click on the mic icon. If you
are on the phone and you are uh uh if
you are on the phone and voice only you
can do that by pressing star six.
We will go through the list in the order
of people raising their hands. We will
take comments from as many individuals
as possible within the time allotted,
which is until 6:30 p.m. Each individual
will have up to 3 minutes to speak. When
it is your turn to speak, your name will
be announced as it appears in the
meeting, and you will be able again to
unmute yourself at that time. If you
join by voice only again, you may unmute
yourself by pressing star six.
Please state your full name and if you
are here representing yourself or if you
are here representing an organization or
company which please announce which
organization or company that you are
representing. You may then make your
statement. There will be a notification
provided to help you complete your
statement when 30 seconds remain in your
time. At three minutes, your microphone
will be muted.
If at the end of the list of people who
would like to speak, there is still
time. Anyone wishing to speak a second
time will be provided with an
opportunity to raise their hands again.
The listening session will end again at
7:30 p.m. And if there are more
individuals who would like to speak than
the time permits, we will encourage you
to join some of the other listening
sessions as they are scheduled. There is
currently another listening session
scheduled for Wednesday, September 3rd
at 300 p.m. To register for that, you
can visit the program website. And
again, the program website uh is
available at this address listed on the
screen.
If you wish to provide a written
statement, options to do so will be
provided at a later time and will be
announced on our program website and
this will occur after the board has been
seated.
Please remember this is a listening
session and the program will not be
answering questions at this time. An FAQ
will be published soon and information
from the listening session may be used
in it especially to answer questions
that may arise.
Thank you. And at this time if for
individuals who are interested in
speaking please click on the hand raise
button and we will go ahead and start.
>> Okay. The first uh request uh Shane
McDaniel, please unmute your line.
>> Okay. Can you hear me now?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Sorry, it wasn't allowing me to
unmute there for a second. Um
>> no worries.
>> Uh yeah, my name is Shane McDaniel. I'm
the I'll be the CEO um and co-founder of
a company called MBS Retreat standing
for mind, body, and spirit. Um we are
going to hopefully be involved in a
couple of different areas of psilocybin
assisted therapy. Um I have experience
in micology growing mushrooms. So um
we're looking to be cultivators. Um I'm
also a certified uh psychedelic um
assisted therapy integration coach. So,
we will I will be providing integration
coaching. Um I will also um be uh at
some point um hopefully opening up a
full service retreat.
What I'd like to know now um is are you
guys looking for additional support
um to help with um subject matter
experts or um you know uh specific to
like integration coaching and and how
that's going to be ran as well as um you
know helping to educate communities be
it local or uh
county or even at the state level. And
then will there be any kind of pilot
programs? Um uh kind of specifically
what I what I would like to find out
about is there going to be anything um
early on maybe dealing with um
uh micro doing and and the efficacies of
micro doing how um that works and if you
guys are interested in that and then
like I said finally if there's any need
for any subject matter expertise or
consulting to help you guys with um you
any information you guys may need. I I
don't know what level of expertise the
members of the board have. That might
mean something nice to know for us is,
you know, maybe on your website kind of
put a little bio of the board members so
we kind of know who we're talking to and
and what kind of expertise you guys
have.
And that's pretty much it. So, um, you
said you're not going to be answering
questions today, though, right?
>> That is correct, Mr. McDaniel.
>> Okay.
>> Right. Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh, next is Cindy Ham.
Cindy, please unmute your line.
Hi everybody. My name is Cindy Ham. I'm
um representing myself and I I think
it's a concern that we should keep in
mind that psilocybin has been used for
many many generations by spiritual
leaders or healers and um in America we
have the right to follow our own
religion in our the comfort of our own
home. So it doesn't necessarily always
require a leader. So I think that it as
one of our um American rights, we should
also be allowed to grow some magic
mushrooms for our own personal medicinal
use at home. And so I'm hoping that that
will be something that will be included
in the uh setup of how medical mushrooms
are going to be handled here in New
Mexico. um whether it be um you know our
our shamans and our gurus or whether it
would be as an individual who would like
to look up some information maybe on the
websites um and try and
um
find mushrooms um integrated into their
own life in through in a way that does
not necessarily involve
um a doctor or a an a clinical office,
that kind of thing. So, um I I just
really feel that it would be one of
those things that people should have um
a choice in the manner in which they
make magic mushrooms a part of their
life. And so I I would hope that that
would be something that we considered
throughout this process.
And um like we did with medical
cannabis, you're allowed to grow
cannabis in small amounts for yourself
or maybe to um give to other people, not
necessarily to make a profit from. But
um I think that
magic mushrooms can be a very positive
um thing for many people and and it I
don't think that it should just be
monetized or corporatized and um or you
know that those permissions necessarily
need
>> 30 seconds remaining
>> that those permissions um should not
always need a a permit or a payment. So,
you know, economically it's very cheap
to grow your own medicine. And so, I
thank you for hearing me and I hope you
um have a good journey with this. Bye.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh next is
Ortiz.
I hope I pronounced your first name at
least somewhat properly. Um, please
unmute your line.
>> Me?
>> Yes. Hello.
>> Hi. Yeah, you got it right. My name is
Kito Ortiz. Um, and I'm a traditional
yera and herbalist here in New Mexico.
uh my practice like many traditional
healing paths here use uh structured
preparation, safe administration and
careful integration which are the same
three phases named in section 3 of SB
219.
So first I urge the department to create
a pathway for culturally trained
non-licensed facilitators to qualify as
clinicians through alternative
certification.
Um, second, under section seven,
approved therapeutic settings should
explicitly include ceremonial and
community spaces. So like healing
circles, sweat lodges, nature settings
as long as they meet safety standards.
And third, section 8 guarantees a tribal
representative on the advisory board,
which is important, but I ask that you
also add a separate seat for a
traditional medicine practitioner.
uh this ensures that representation for
all traditional healers including
non-tribal kuranderas yeras and others
who practice whose practices are rooted
in New Mexico's heritage. Um this bill
allows adding new qualifying conditions.
So I um ask you to please include
cultural well-being and community
well-being so that people without um a
western diagnosis can still benefit from
this program. And um and finally, by
honoring both medical science and the
cultural traditions that have stewarded
this medicine for generations, this
program can truly refle reflect New
Mexico's diversity and history. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Uh next is Amy Wong Hope. Amy,
please unmute your mic.
Amy.
Okay. Hearing nothing, we'll go to the
next person.
Uh, next is uh, Denali Wilson.
Please unmute your line.
>> Good evening. I I hope we can come back
to Amy if she's able to come back into
the queue. Um, but my name is Denali
Wilson. I am the New Mexico director of
strategic support for the Healing
Advocacy Fund, which is a nonprofit
that's committed to expanding and
protecting safe, affordable, and
equitable access to psychedelic healing
for all those who need it. And as the
department develops this program, I
wanted to share a few priorities.
First, um, among them is safety. People
seeking psilocybin care deserve strong
protections and we recommend clear but
balanced guard rails with different
levels of licensing and training
uh, for each stage of care and each
individual professional involved so that
requirements match the responsibility of
each role and each profession.
Facilitators should be trained in a
number of things, but some important
topics are supportive touch, power
dynamics, relational boundaries,
cultural responsibility, when to seek
medical help. Um, and we also encourage
the development of a code of ethics
along with adverse event reporting and
response protocols so that the program
can protect both patients and
continually improve.
I want to talk also about affordability
and equity. Uh many of us would agree
that access should not be limited to
those who can afford to pay thousands of
dollars for care. Regulations should
minimize unnecessary costs while paving
the way for eventual insurance coverage.
Some things we can do would be to, as
the previous speaker said, recognize a
broad definition of clinical clinician
under the statute, permitting group care
models, uh authorizing the involvement
of peer support workers, traditional
healers, and other alternatively
licensed care team members, and
supporting and developing claims data
research to encourage thirdparty
payment. We also support diverse
settings for treatments, you know, from
a therapy office, inhome care for
homebound patients to outdoor or retreat
spaces in order to maximize access and
choice, but also again to ensure
affordability and flexibility. When it
when it comes to ensuring equity, um we
urge the state legislature to fully fund
the program's equity fund and are
committed to supporting the department
of health's budget request when the time
comes for that. Additionally, if
adopted, any kinds of licensing
preferences, training, scholarships, or
other opportunities should prioritize
indigenous communities, those most
impacted by the war on drugs, and those
who have cultural ties to the
traditional use of psilocybin.
Things like advertising rules, if
adopted, could also be used to protect
>> seconds remaining
>> to protect Thank you. protect against
cultural misappropriation.
Um, and as they can, just to close,
regulation should be as uh adaptive and
flexible as possible, incorporating new
evidence and community input over time
and ensuring program viability in the
long run. So, thank you so much. Um,
appreciate your time and your
leadership.
>> Thank you.
Um, we'll go back to um Amy.
Amy Wong Hope, please unmute your line.
Again, to do that, if you're connected
via um the Teams um app on your
computer, use the hand icon.
If you're on a phone, you can press the
three dots in the menu and the hand icon
will appear. And if you're on a phone um
through voice only, press um star six to
unmute your line.
Okay, it looks like Amy has lowered her
hand, so we will go to the next
um person, and that is Brett Phelps.
Brett, please unmute your line.
Okay, looks like he lowered his hand.
Um, let's hear next from
Greg Doherty.
Craig, please unmute your line.
Hello. Can you hear me?
>> Uh, yes. Please go ahead.
>> Thank you. Hello. My name is Craig Dohy.
Uh, I'm with Chillax. Uh, primarily
we've been a uh cannabis uh retailer
throughout New Mexico or here in Rio,
New Mexico. Um in the uh past uh we have
uh been a cultivator of mushrooms like
lion's mane and reishi and here in New
Mexico it seems like very little people
have uh experience generally about
mushrooms but it seems to be um a very
expensive endeavor in uh in other areas.
If we look at Oregon right now, if you
were to go there to try to participate,
it would start roughly around like
$2,500
for just one session. And those uh are
just quite astronomical. I would like to
just put forward that, you know, the
regulation still is in effect, but not
to overregulate as to price out most New
Mexicans from therapeutic use. Um the
other thing as well um one thing that
we've noticed from a lot of the things
in Oregon too is that you know with the
facilities we've seen a lot of
facilities kind of come and go and
unfortunately it seems like that's
really due to like the regulation of the
facilitators themselves and to where
they can actually practice and
participate. Um, it seems like Colorado
has done different ways to where you can
actually have a facilitator outside of
just the normal facility to where they
can go and participate in other um,
designated areas. Um, so I would just
like to bring those to attention. Thank
you so much for the time.
>> Thank you.
Okay, we'll go next to Maximillian
Sparza.
Let me allow your mic. You can please
unmute your line.
Hi everyone. My name is Maxmleon Esparza
and I am a mushroom farmer and
international advocate of fungi and
mushrooms for the last four years now.
And I'm here representing my
organization mycelium matters. And I'm
also here because I have had a profound
healing experiences with psilocybin um
during COVID for my depression and for
my ADD. Um I think it's important that
this program is accessible, affordable,
and inclusive. Um, as far as
accessibility, I think it's important
that people across the region of New
Mexico are serviced um well along with a
bipac, black, indigenous people of color
and lowincome communities as well as
atome services for people who have
disabilities.
And I also find that outofstate reciproc
uh reciprocity would be very uh helpful
and important as I was a medical
cannabis reciprocal patient um back in
2018 and 19 with with New Mexico and it
helped me greatly for my depression um
and with my sleep and appetite. Um and
then I also think accessibility um from
the licensing aspect is important um as
there should be multiple licenses um and
no monopolies um create access for
cultivators for practitioners um for
labs and it would be um important to
focus on the whole fruing body of
mushroom. Um although I think there are
patients who will seek out synthetic uh
version of psilocybin because that is
what they might find most comfortable
working with but it is important to have
a focus and respect for the whole fruing
body of mushroom. Um and and getting uh
starting up early with lab permitting
and and consulting um with labs in
Colorado or California would also be
very helpful. So early on mushrooms can
be lab tested um and and we can see you
know how we're dosing people and and
what compounds there are in these
mushrooms.
Um
and then I I find uh inclusivity
um it is important to be inclusive and
acknowledge all stakeholders who have
been historically involved and currently
involved as well. Um which is indigenous
people and tribal members and veterans
and first responders. Um it is important
that we include all voices and and paths
uh people walk and and get their
feedback for this program. And lastly, I
think research is also um
>> 30 seconds remaining. focusing on
research early on. Um, collecting data
from cultivators, from universities,
from practitioners and research
companies and keeping this program
evidence-based um, and opening up the
program to other uh, cultural practices
and health disorders and illnesses um,
like migraine disorder, which my partner
suffers from and has helped has found
great relief in psilocybin along with
phantom limb syndrome and and so forth.
Thank you.
>> Okay, next we'll
go to Brett Phelps.
Please unmute your line.
Brett, if you're speaking, we cannot
hear you.
>> Okay, we'll move on.
If you need to lower your hand because
you no longer wish to provide comment,
you can press star six
or um the microphone um button on the on
the app.
Um
next is Brenda Burgard.
Brenda, please unmute your line.
Brenda, it appears as though your line
was unmuted momentarily and is muted
again.
>> Okay, can you hear me now?
>> Yes, your three minutes starts now.
>> Thank you for having me. Um, this is a
great opportunity. My name is Brenda
Burgard. I am the president of
Decriminalization for Psychedelics here
in New Mexico and we're um an
organization uh nonprofit and we support
um personal use um c um cultivating for
personal use as well. religious freedom.
Um uh we respect indigenous rights and
we also um are providing information
about psychedelics um and promoting
education safety research and law
changes to reduce incarceration and
mental health support.
And at the same time, you know, we want
to be um inclusive of all the people in
the community of New Mexico to be
involved with this so that we can join
together and provide
support for each other uh using uh
especially psilocybin and for um people
who want to use it for
um many uses. So um being part of this
organization, I'm hoping to um give our
full support throughout the community.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Brenda. And uh just uh
because we are just over half an hour
into the listening session, I just want
and I know we have had additional people
join in. Um, I just wanted to repeat
some of the instructions. If you're
interested in speaking, you will have 3
minutes to speak. To indicate you would
like to speak is please raise the hand
within teams. The way to do that is if
you are on a computer, click on the hand
icon near the top of the teams window
and it says raise under the icon. Uh if
you are on teams app on a phone, please
press the ellipses or the three dots in
the menu and then click on the hand icon
which will appear at that time. If
you're joining through phone and voice
only, please press star five to raise or
lower your hand. Once we call on you uh
in order to unmute your uh microphone,
if you are on the computer, please click
on the little microphone icon in the
upper right hand section of the team's
window. If you are on the f on a phone
with voice only, you can press star six.
And Kathy, may we go to our next
speaker?
>> Yes, our next speaker is Mitchell
Dingle. Please unmute your line.
Hello, my name is Mitch Dingle and I
have been heavily involved with the
medical cannabis industry since 2017
back in the DO days. I have worked for
many legacy producers. So, I have a
brief comment to add to the discussion.
I implore the department to please be
mindful and have a cap in mind of how
many cultivation or production licenses
will be granted. The application process
should be fair and equal for all, but we
do not want a flooded market as it will
no longer be medical or patient centric
and will inevitably become a profit
ccentric business model. It is my
personal opinion that the medical
psilocybin program mirror how successful
the medical cannabis program was ran as
it was life-changing for thousands of
New Mexicans who needed the medical
relief. and it was a huge honor to have
been a part of that. I just want to say
kudos and props to the department of
health. That is all. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Next, we'll go to um Gregory
Evans. Please unmute your line.
>> Hello. Uh, thank you everyone for being
here. This is wonderful to see everybody
show up. Just making sure that you can
hear me.
>> We can hear you.
>> Um, we've got thunder and lightning and
I've lost internet twice, so bear with
me if I disappear.
So the biggest things that I want to
talk about is testing,
dosage,
understanding, standardization
and uh research and data collection with
analytical testing. There are some
people
some companies that are doing it well
and some companies that are not doing it
as well. There is still yet to be full
standardization
in how people analyze HLC data. Um, so
I'm currently very interested in how we
can create an open-source portal to
uh allow disperate labs to go through a
unified processing and data analytics
function.
The
value in that is pointing back to an
earlier comment about respecting the
fruing body and understanding the
diversity of organic biomass. Different
genetics, different growing conditions
and alkaloid pro profiles will um will
exist and they should and that's
important. But we also for patients
especially people who are not familiar
and comfortable with landscape
definitely need a PCN level equivalent
to all organic biomass and that requires
extensive testing. Um, moving into
dosage and standardization,
understanding what a micro dose is, what
a mini dose, therapeutic and super
therapeutic doses are is super important
because some people just think eating
mushrooms means stuffing a handful in
your face. Um, but what we're really
moving towards in a medical market is
understanding that there are other ways
to approach this. And I'm not against
eating a bunch of mushrooms and having a
spiritual experience, but that is not
the correct pathway for every single
person. I want to make sure that
pathways are diverse and accessible.
Um, research um I mean I just think
research, research, research.
>> You have 30 seconds remaining.
>> Um, that's really all I have. I'll say
research one more time.
>> Thank you.
Okay, next we go to uh James Brown.
>> James, please unmute your line.
>> Hello everyone and thank you for
allowing me to have a few minutes with
you today. My name is James Brown and
I'm an independent pharmacist here in
New Mexico. Um I was a very big advocate
and one of the veteran of eight years
with the Navy. Um, I'm also a disabled
vet and so my advocacy work drives
access as well as access to all New
Mexicans for this very powerful
substance. Um, I've been trained in
psilocybin in Oregon. Um and so I'm a
facilitator trained um individual um
coming to you guys asking
the department of health to establish a
framework that will focus on again as
the theme says research clinical trials
on the therapeutic use of psychedelics
as well as primarily psilocybin at this
point. education and public awareness
campaign of the public. Um that should
include the general public, specifically
professionals, disabled veterans, um
Native Americans, first people, um and
all other New Mexicans. And and that's a
very broad in New Mexico, as you guys
know. Um from I I would like to see from
north to south, um from east to west,
all New Mexico needs to be represented
here.
um licensing of mental health
professionals
uh authorized to um administer
psychedelics psilocybin um as part of
their treatment programs and look at
those um caveats is to um individuals
with insurance lure uh protection
protection in the the setting will be
very important to discuss and bills to
uh come up with um setting is very
important with this um as well as lure
with grandfathering ing um for other
people who maybe don't have access to
blending. Um but the home setting it'll
be very large focus as well as for the
end of life therapy. Um I'm a very big
believer of having um these settings in
homes. um as long as you have consent
forms that I'm very familiar with and as
long as that's in place and the lensure
is there and and insurance is there
people should be allowed to have these
rituals these ceremonies these personal
experiences and journeys at home um and
so I really want to challenge that and
say we don't want to be um anything has
to do personally um you know the
Colorado model or the Oregon model this
is New Mexico we need to establish a New
Mexican model that is geared around New
Mexico
>> have 30 seconds remaining.
>> Having access and also protecting
traditional use of you know their
American tribes is essential because
that will preserve their cultural
heritage and practices. Um the
department of health shall develop
public education campaigns
and again develop these guidelines that
develop safe use including as you guys
hear dosing settings and patient
screening forms. That's going to be very
big is intake. Um I have not heard that
yet. Intake is going to be very big. And
what are we doing?
>> Your time is up.
>> Thank you again.
>> Thank you.
Okay. Next we'll go to um May S. Please
unmute your line.
>> Hello, my name is May and I work as a
pastoral minister. Um I see clients and
um have been working with many people
who come for me out of state who have
endeavored in different types of
treatments and are lacking the
integration for these powerful moments
for themselves. They have gone into a
medical realm, been given the dose, sit
there for 20 minutes, observed, and then
they leave and they don't understand
what is happening to their bodies and
their minds. And so I would really push
forth and kind of echo what I heard from
Kinto Ortiz is that there are different
practitioners out there that are not
just medical providers or mental health
counselors that can help make sense of
the integration process that is so
important to this type of work. If we
don't integrate it, it becomes almost
voyeristic. It becomes almost
recreational. And so this is a huge part
of this process. It's not just the
education and the research, the
licensing. We need people that can help
make sense of the spiritual unfolding
for themselves and help our clients
integrate these magic moments, these
momentous changes that are happening
within them. Without this integration,
this is this is voyeristic. this is
recreational and could very much verge
on taking something like you know
penicellin or um you know
anti-depressants and so I do agree with
the screening I do agree with the ethics
the research the education but we do
need to bring this into a holistic sense
so that we're not bringing people into
these realms and then dropping them back
into this world that doesn't make sense
to us we need integration. Thank you.
Thank you.
>> Okay, I apologize. Um, it looks like I
might have skipped over um Brett Phelps.
Um, Brett, your light, your mic is um
open. Please unmute your line.
>> Yes. Good evening. I think the third
time is the charm. Just had to get onto
my phone instead of the computer. Um,
thank you. Thank you guys very much. My
name is Brett Phelps. Uh, I am an
attorney based in Las Vegas, New Mexico.
Um, here representing myself. Um, no
stake in this other than just wanting to
see the the program succeed. Um, so
first of all, I would just like to to
thank our our legislators,
our department of health, and all the
advocates who made this program happen.
um we have a very special opportunity
here in in New Mexico to be a leader um
in this space not only for the country
but across the world and I think the
most important thing that uh the
department should be looking at to um to
achieve a successful program is patient
accessibility. Um how do we how do we
make this accessible and affordable to
as many people as as possible? And I
think the first uh element of that that
I would mention is to make sure that
these regulations are not overly
burdensome. Um there's been a lot of
comments already about being able to
incorporate as many people into this
program as providers and producers. um
as long as we can do that safely. But if
it's if it's overly burdensome for
regulations, um the the traditional
practitioners, the the smaller, you
know, the mom and pop kind of operations
are not going to be able to are not
going to be able to to thrive. Um, the
other element that I would really like
to highlight, um, particularly coming
from, uh, from the northeast of of New
Mexico is we really need to focus on how
to provide services to our rural
communities. Um, access to health care
in rural areas is is already very
difficult. And so, the program, you
know, should really get get creative in
looking at how we can adequ adequately
serve our our rural communities. Um, and
so I think there's a lot of different
ways to to do that, but that's just
something that I, you know, I highlight
because it's easy for a lot of our state
to to kind of get lost in the
discussions. Um, and so would just
really really ask the department to to
focus on, you know, how can we provide
this service to as many people as
possible across our our very vast state.
Um, so with that, thank you very much
for the time. Thank you for your
patience with me having to go through
this a couple times and getting on and
yeah, really looking forward to see
where the program goes. So, thank you
again.
>> Thank you. And we did have one other
person who had had some issues earlier.
Um Amy Wong Hope, would you like to
speak at this time? If you would, um we
can unmute. There we go. Perfect. Uh,
you can go ahead and unmute your mic,
Amy, and we'll go ahead and start it.
>> There we go. We can hear you.
>> I think it might have worked. Oh my
goodness. Thank you so much for your
perseverance. And thank you, Denali, for
uh helping me out. And also Brett. Okay,
so uh my name is Amy Wong Hope. I'm a
clinical social worker and a trauma
therapist and I run a psychedelic
studies program at Southwestern College.
Um, my main concern is about how to make
this treatment affordable for New
Mexicans. And I think that's on
everyone's mind. Um, I know the
regulations have to be there for
accountability for the practitioners and
safety for the state of New Mexico
actually taking this step and doing
this. So, thank you New Mexico
Department of Health and um, our
legislators for doing this. And um, this
is very exciting. Um, but what happens
is the cost for the minimum cost really
for every journeyer is probably going to
be about 1,500 and that would be
inexpensive and that's due to the high
cost of rent for um where people can use
psilocybin in say in Colorado in Oregon
and um that's due to the rental fees. um
uh journeyers will pay a minimum of like
$500 to $800 just for the room alone or
that day use. And so I'm wondering if
the board can and the New Mexico
Department of Health can consider some
sort of comprehensive real estate suite
of regulations um that would allow um
existing licensed clinicians under the
psilocybin program to practice within
different environments. Um, many of the
people who are renting are also renting
from their landlords and landlords might
have mortgages that are federal. So,
there needs to be some rules and
regulations to protect those landlords
as well. So, um, that's one of the big
questions I have. And then um the other
one is uh just as Brett said, I I would
love to see more ruralbased
interventions for those to be affordable
groups psilocybin models that would
allow people to access this treatment.
Um and then third party payments
possibly from Medicaid uh payers uh for
this as well. Um, I really want to see
that traditional medicine facilitators
who don't go through traditional
training programs can get licensed and
um that they just need to maybe know
about or agree to a certain type of
safety standard so that there could be
these interventions in um different
nation tribe and PBLO locations. Um my
next thing is really about budget and
wondering what kind of budget
>> remaining
>> the program um is there divers
diversification in the funding because
if it's going to be based on licensing
fees I'm very very worried because in
Oregon that has really um been a problem
only 50% of facilitators renewed their
licenses and so that program is really
in bankruptcy. So that's it. I want to
thank you all for this and uh these
listening sessions and excited to see
what happens.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Next we will go to um Charles
Godfrey.
>> Charles, please unmute your line.
>> Thank you. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Uh I'm a retired physician. Uh and my
voice is one of caution. uh I have been
along alive alive long enough to have
benefited from uh drugs like psilocybin
in the 60s and also witnessed to the
repression that occurred for 50 years uh
after that. Uh 219 is a very progressive
law and a very repressive atmosphere in
this country. Uh I think uh I I'm really
pleased that this passed the
legislature, but I think that we have to
stick to what the law dictates, which is
uh use for specific diagnosis uh with a
medical model. Uh my own opinion is that
psilocybin probably is more beneficial
uh in a spiritual way uh than in a
medical way, but I think uh we are not
there in terms of what uh the law has
authorized. Uh and I not that you can't
have both and I think you often do have
both. Uh but I think because the law
dictates that we uh follow certain uh
diagnosis and uh a medical model of use
uh and uh because of this u previous
history of repression I think we have to
stick to the law.
>> Thank you.
Okay, next we will go to Dr. Lisa
Martinez.
Please unmute your line.
>> Hi there. Um, my name is Dr. Lisa
Martinez and I'm a practitioner at
Kanderismo in Colorado.
And as we're witnessing how things are
evolving here in Colorado, I just really
want to encourage that as New Mexico
implements the medical psilocybin act
that they have a really amazing
opportunity here. Especially since New
Mexico recognizes traditional healing
through the unlicensed healthcare
practice act. you you all name
kuranderas medicine people and other
traditional healers in that law as
carrying generational knowledge and it's
trusted by the community there in
Colorado we're seeing a lot of
difficulties with the accessibility
already um especially when it comes to
traditional healers because they weren't
specifically included our law doesn't
cover by name uh traditional
practitioners we have a a consumer
uh protection act but but we're not
named explicitly. Um so we have a lot of
things that we in and hoops that we have
to jump through in order to practice
often. Um, you know, our communities
have a lot of deep ties to our sacred
medicines and oftentimes we're the ones
that are left out or we're pushed to the
margins and excluding the traditional
healers is going to create a really
difficult and maybe even like a a
two-tiered system that privilege it
privileges western clinical providers um
and sidelining the people whose
communities have safeguarded these
sacred plants for so long and espec
especially our our our our mushroom
medicine too, you know. Um so I'm just
really urging the department of health
and the advisory board to explicitly
include and protect traditional healers
in this framework. Um provide cultural
training, apprenticeships and community
recognition. It must be respected as
valid qualifications
alongside clinical lensure. We can work
with elders. Um there's ways to
acknowledge and verify and validate. Um
and also include those ethical, you
know, code of ethics and safety training
in that. Um this is really about equity
and cultural safety and ensuring that
those who may benefit from the
psilocybin's healing potential can also
access it in a way that's safe and
respectful and align with cultural
traditions. Um I just, you know, it's
something that we're witnessing. um I
feel really passionate about and I
>> have 30 seconds remaining.
>> I just really love that New Mexico has
that law in place and this is a really
incredible opportunity to excel that um
and to see it really blossom into
something beautiful. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Um at this time we don't see
any additional hands. If there is
somebody who is interested in speaking
and who has not yet spoken, uh please go
ahead and raise your hand at this time.
And again to in order to raise your hand
if you are on uh joining us on a
computer on the teams app there just go
to the top of the teams window and click
on the hand icon. Uh if you are on the
team's app on a phone pre please press
the ellipses in the menu and then the
hand icon which will appear. Uh and if
you are joining through phone and
through voice only you can press star
five to either raise or lower your hand.
We'll give people a few moments to raise
their hands if there's again anyone else
who has not yet spoken who would like to
speak at this time.
Okay, we'll go to Chris Disco.
Uh Chris, please unmute your line. Sorry
if I botched your last name.
Hello everyone. I just want my name is
Chris Pascus and I'm an independent
advocate and uh ambassador for the oil
carts project. I just wanted to thank
everybody for their comments tonight and
tell everyone that I'm just really
looking forward to um this whole process
and continuing to work and talk with you
all about how to implement uh all of
this. and um it's just very exciting and
I thank you all for your time and coming
to this meeting uh and for bringing up
all these uh wonderful points. Um thank
you very much.
>> Thank you Chris and uh Greg, we're just
going to go ahead and skip you for just
a little bit. We want to make sure
everybody has the opportunity to speak
first and then we'll come back to you
for a second round uh once we are able
to go through everybody.
Okay.
>> Okay. Next we have Philip Toledo.
Philip, please unmute your line.
This is Philip Toledo representing
Shroom Biosis
which is a company just starting in the
cultivating mushrooms and cannabis.
We hope to engage with the medical
industry and supplying high-end product.
Please reach out. Thank you for your
time.
>> Thank you. Is there anybody else who
would like to speak at this time? Again,
if you would like to for the first time,
if you would like to, please just raise
your hand in the Teams app and program.
And again, we'll give people a few
moments to be able to do so. And if
there is not anyone, we will start on uh
if anybody who has already spoken would
like to speak again.
Okay, if there is anybody who has
already spoken and would like a second
turn to speak, please go ahead and raise
your hand at this Fine.
Gregory Evans, please unmute your line.
Uh, I just want to say Chris, it is so
good to hear your voice. everybody else
um that I'm know thank you so much for
everything. Um the
I forgot to mention the first time I
spoke I am independent. I'm just a
person who has received so much from
this medicine that I am
uh compelled to support it in a way that
I feel allows it to exist in a a manner
that
provides
increased access to people who may not
have known that this is medicine that
can help them. whether it's physically
or mentally or spiritually or some
combination of all those things. So that
being said, I wanted to echo a bunch of
statements about home cultivation. I
think right now we have current
precedent legally in the in the state of
New Mexico where home cultivation is
fine as long as you don't pick the
mushrooms which kind of like kind of
makes it okay which has put our state
in a space where people are cultivating.
And so there is a lot of really valuable
uh knowledge here in the state. Um and
we should
really leverage that.
The
I lost my notes.
Access and equity. I'm a huge huge I
will I will shout from the rooftops the
value of home like home use, home daily
use. I think it's super important for
integration models to allow access to
spit prescription level doses that would
be in the micro and mini categories of
dosing so that after a giant experience
when we're folding these like
revelations back into our lives eg
integration that we have some sort of
platform of support in medically to help
that process.
Um, I'm sure I'm running close to the
time. Um, but yeah, um, I have a lot to
say about policy and stuff, but I think
kind of push that to a later more
developed conversation.
>> Thank you.
Hey, next we have Amy
um Wong Hope again. Amy, please unmute
your line.
>> Hi. There were just a few more points I
wanted to touch on. One is about um
educational awareness with uh the New
Mexican community, especially the
substance use community or substance pro
use provider community as well as the
nation tribe and pblo that are
throughout the state of New Mexico. Um I
know there is a tribal liaison um that
the DOH has engaged and my hope is that
there is a very robust
uh advisory council member as well as
subcommittee that supports that advisory
council member as well as the tribal
leaison and ensuring that there is
adequate um uh awareness made within
those nation tribe and PBLO communities
about psilocybin as an option and the
ways in which they might want to
implement those programs. and their own
sovereign nations as well. So, uh, the
request would be for the New Mexico
advisory board on DOH to ensure that any
rules and regulations do not impede or
cause any problems for those nation
tribe and PBLO if if they choose to
implement their own programs
um, psilocybin programs or or other um,
uh, psychedelic assisted therapy
programs or or healing programs. Um my
other um question or concern is about
training and training and licensing of
the licensed clinicians within the
psilocybin program. And my hope that
there would be an option to have a very
New Mexicanbased creation of that
training program rather than um
psychedelic assisted therapy or
psilocybin training programs that come
from other states because I think New
Mexico is a very very different
population to treat and for our um
psilocybin treatments to be really
appropriate to the culture here, it
needs to be the the trainers and and the
contextual program curriculum needs to
be specific to our state. So, thank you
very much again.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay, next we'll go to May S. May,
please unmute your line.
>> Thanks again for having this meeting. I
think it's so important and it's such a
beautiful act that New Mexico is looking
at integrating this into medical
practices. I don't know if this was, you
know, be beating a dead horse, but I
want to reiterate that this this
practice has been in use by cultures
historically throughout time. And we
need to give credence to those cultures
that have this experience and refer to
them not just in the medical realm and
medical testing but we we we do need to
give credo to the peoples that have been
using this medicine and to refer to them
for their expertise. This is a
generational expertise that they have
and so I do hope that it is a holistic
approach where we are consulting with
the cultures that have been using this.
Um, thank you so much for your time and
I'm I'm just so happy to see all these
people here. So, thank you all.
>> Thank you.
>> Next, we'll go to Marina Robbins.
Marina, please unmute your line.
>> Hello, my name is Marina. I'm a fourth
year doctor of public health candidate
at UC Berkeley and I'm currently
conducting research in on the Navajo
reservation. I'm D from Windock,
Arizona. And so I'm trying to understand
the implications that these psilocybin
legislative efforts within the four
corners Arizona, New Mexico, Colorado,
and Utah have um on the tribal
government system, naval healthcare
practitioners, traditional
practitioners. And so I just want to
echo two things. Um, one the previous
speaker made about highlighting
indigenous cultures and the ceremonies
that have been created to hold mushrooms
as a medicine, as a container, as a
vessel because ceremony is a technology.
Um, when we're going into other realms
with these medicines, we're opening
portals, we're opening doors, and
sometimes things get let in that
shouldn't be there or maybe we might get
lost. So, there's a reason for ceremony.
There's a reason that these medicines
are held in a certain container. And
then Amy Wong talked about education.
Um, when I'm approaching the Navajo
Nation, we don't have stories about
mushrooms. We have one story that they
make you go blind. And so those are
stories that need to be heard and I
think education needs to be built into
that um at different levels from the
youth to the adults to the elders. Um
different exposure. How is psilocybin
being talked about at the mainstream
level through social media through Tik
Tok, Reddit, what have you and what what
information is out there? Um and how do
we inform tribal leaders about
psilocybin? What is it? what did what uh
taboos come with it? What uh stories
come with it? So education, information
building um I think uh needs to be out
there in order for tribes to make an
informed decision about whether they
want psilocybin assisted therapy within
their um reservation boundaries within
their healthcare system. Um I'll stop
there. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
And once again we have uh come to the
end of our list of the individuals with
their hands raised. So if there is
someone who would like to speak whether
you have spoken previously or have not
spoken at all at this time please go
right on ahead and raise your hand. And
again if you are on a computer on teams
just click on the hand icon near the top
of the teams window. If you are on a uh
the team's app on your phone, please
press the ellipses or the three dots in
the menu and then the hand icon will
appear for you to be able to select it.
If you're joining on a phone through
voice only, please press star five to
raise or lower your hand.
So since we have a little bit of a pause
um for those who had joined a little bit
later um uh just our update from the
program was that currently the program
is working with both the office of the
governor and the department of health
secretary to asend
the medical psilocybin advisory board
and that uh we are planning on having
the board be seated in September which
has previously been announced. Once the
board is seated there will be several
additional public meetings and listening
sessions scheduled. Some of those public
meetings will be conducted in person and
some of them will be virtual or virtual
or hybrid. Um, we do have another
listening session that is scheduled for
tomorrow or for next Wednesday,
September 3rd, starting at 300 p.m. And
to register for that listening session,
if you would like, just please visit the
program website, which is showing on the
screen right now, um, and just register
uh, for that. If you do share the
information about the listening sessions
to others, please let them know that
they can register by visiting the links
on the website rather than emailing to
the program. Uh when they email
individuals email to the program, we
simply have to refer them back to the
registration links. So please make sure
if you are doing so and we appreciate by
the way when individuals or
organizations are amplifying the notices
that we have sent out. Um and so uh
thank you very much for doing that. Just
please let them know to go to the
website and to register through the
links provided in the website.
And again, if for some reason uh you do
not get the opportunity to speak today
or if you just do not want to voice here
on a a public forum, you are welcome to
provide a written statement. But those
options will be provided at a later time
after the board has been seated.
And so I'd like to ask at this time, are
there additional individuals who would
like to speak? And again, this could be
someone who has not spoken or if someone
has already spoken.
There are currently no additional hands
raised.
>> So, we have this meeting scheduled until
7:30 p.m. tonight. We will continue to
remain on the line in the event that
individuals join late so that they have
the opportunity to express their
thoughts, comments, and ideas. Um, and
so we will stay and remain here at that
point uh until 7:30 this evening.
And I should mention individuals are
welcome to stay to hear in case anyone
else does join and provide uh any
information or comments. Um however it
is not required. We will have uh the
listening sessions will be posted online
uh after they have concluded. Uh it may
take a week or so for them to be
published on our website but we will do
so uh in the near future. And also uh as
mentioned earlier um the information and
the questions that have been asked
tonight will be utilized and will be um
uh will be utilized in the creation of
our FAQ which we hope to publish
We do have about 15 minutes remaining in
our session. So once again if there is
anybody who is interested in speaking
further you please go ahead and raise
your hand. And again, the method to
raise your hand is if you are on a
computer on Teams, please click on the
hand icon that is near the top of the
Teams window. If you are on an app on
your phone or a tablet, please press the
ellipses, the three dots that are in the
menu, and then click on the hand icon.
If you're joining on a phone through
voice only, please press star five to
raise or lower your hand.
Currently there are no raised hands.
I would again like to thank everybody
who is here on the call in the listening
session with us today. If there is
anyone who has uh thought of something
they would like to add at this time, uh
please go ahead and raise your hand and
we'll be more than happy to hear your
comments, ideas, and suggestions.
And for those who would just like to sit
here quietly with us a little bit, I
recommend some deep breathing
techniques. Thanks.
There was just someone new admitted into
the meeting.
>> Thank you Kathy. Um just so that
everyone is aware uh we are just taking
any individuals who would like to make
comments uh can go ahead and just raise
their hand. So for the new individuals
who have joined, if you are on a
computer on the team's uh program,
click on the hand icon near the top of
the window. Uh if you are on the team's
app on your phone, please press the
three ellipses or the three dots and uh
then the hand icon will appear and you
can select it. or if you are on a phone
and voice only, pressing star five will
allow you to raise or lower your hand.
And again, we appreciate everybody who
has made comments today. But at this
time, if anybody would like to make any
additional comments, you are welcome to.
And again, we will stay on the line
until 7:30, our appointed time to end
the listening session in the event other
individuals would like to make comments
or join late.
And for those who were not here in the
very beginning, my name is Dr. Dominic
Zerlo. I am the director for the New
Mexico Department of Health Center for
Medical Cannabis and Psilocybin.
and some of our other team members here
today from our center is Brenda our
Brenda Martinez our deputy director
Rosalie Nava our health education
program manager our health education
team members who are Carmen Batista
Katie Fryag and Adrien Estrada and we
have helping us with technical issues
and timekeeping Kathy Ajieri who is our
IT project manager
So, I'd like to thank each of them for
assisting and being present today.
They are a part of the team that will
allow this program to be successful.
There are currently no hands raised.
Ah, we have Jessica,
>> please unmute your line.
Jessica, if you are speaking, we can't
hear you. Uh, at this point, you do need
to unmute your mic by using either the
icon that is usually in the upper right
on the the Teams app or if you were on
your phone, it is star six. Uh if you
are voice only, if you are on the phone
app, it is at the bottom of the screen
or is usually at the bottom of the
screen. So you just need to unmute that.
Jessica's line is still muted.
Jessica, we will come back to you
shortly uh to see if uh you've been able
to unmute. In the meantime, we will go
to uh Amy Wong Hope. Amy, go ahead.
>> Hi, just wanted to say Jessica, I was
there. You might want to log out and log
back in because that's what solved it
for me. Okay. Um and but I did have a
comment. Um, one is, uh, actually the
person who just left. Um, I did want to
wonder about, you know, what will be
what what types of people will be
allowed to be the the licensed
clinicians within the psilocybin
program. And, um, something that was
brought up to me by the Oregon folks is
that they were not allowed to be uh,
natural medicine facilitators in the
state of Colorado in their psilocybin
program. Um so that is a wondering you
know how how vast or wide uh we might
make uh our uh uh requirements or who
who can apply to be a psilocybin
facilitator. The other one is I wonder
about uh paliative care uh clinicians uh
doctors and also death doulas um and
hope that death doulas would be allowed
to be uh licensed clinical licensed uh
psilocybin clinicians within this
program as well because I think death
doulas really understand and and hold
the that process of uh transition for
people and um and also something that
the paliotative care community talks
about frequently and I I not sure we
heard from many paliotative care uh
providers today. I hope we hear some in
the future, but I know that one thing
that they've wanted in in all the other
states is to be allowed to provide
psilocybin sessions inside the home. And
another request that I would have uh for
me just as a social worker that I would
love to see is possibly an an expansion
of who is allowed to undergo psilocybin
treatment would not just be the person
who's having distress from the terminal
illness but the family members who are
caretaking of the person who is in the
process of um passing away from a
terminal illness. So, I hope that that
might that that rule might expand within
the the um the way that it's interpreted
to allow for that, too. Um so, I think
that's it. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Amy.
>> And then I did see that Jessica had
rejoined. Um Jessica, are you uh Oh, and
it looks like Jessica is leaving again.
So, okay.
Well, we do have a few minutes left. Are
there other individuals who would like
to speak?
Uh, and it looks like Jessica, you have
joined again. Um, would you like to
speak? If you would just unmute.
your line is still muted, Jessica.
>> Oh, finally. Hi.
>> I'm sorry.
>> Hello, Jessica. Welcome.
>> Hi. Hi, thank you. Thank you for letting
me in like three different times. Um, I
was saying uh that we ran out of
internet in truth of consequences where
I am and I think there was a TDS outage
in several other places in in the state.
So, we just got it back and I wasn't
able to join until now even on the
phone. Um, so I'm glad I got a a chance
to meet you all for the last minutes of
this session and um I'm hoping that um
maybe the session has been recorded and
I could listen to it afterwards and I
did register for the one on September as
well.
>> Well, I think that is a legitimate
question we can answer. Jessica, we are
recording this and after the sessions
are complete um we will be posting them
to our website and so just look on the
website over the next couple of weeks uh
for the actual recordings.
>> Okay, thank you so much.
>> You're welcome. I'm glad that you were
able to join.
>> Thank you.
>> And so uh is there anyone else who would
like to speak? We have three minutes
left. So, time for one more individual
if someone has any last minute items
they'd like to express.
There are no new hands raised.
We have just a couple minutes more. So
once again, if there's anybody who has
uh any last minute items they'd like to
bring up, please do so now. And if not,
if people think of things. In the
meantime, again, we will have the other
listening session next Wednesday,
September 3rd, starting at 300 p.m.
And to register for that one, you go to
the same place on our website uh in the
announcement sections in order to go
ahead and register for that session.
And I'll make one final call. Is there
anybody who would like to say anything
at this time?
>> Hey, with that being the case,
>> oh, thank you, Kathy. With that being
the case, we'd like to thank you again
for joining us tonight. Um, and uh, we
would just like to also mention that for
other additional announcements, please
check out our website um, where you'll
be able to see announcements as they
move forward. We are also working with
our communications team in order to
create a list serve. Um, and once that
is available, it will be announced on
our website. Uh, Brenda, uh, I believe
that you have you have a comment,
Brenda. Uh if you would like uh Oh, no.
>> Brenda, unmute your mic.
>> Yes. I just wanted to say thank you for
having this. Um this is a really
wonderful way to get everybody together
to make a comment on what the DO is um
doing and coming forward with all of
this. It's it's wonderful to see and I
wanted to thank you very much for having
all of us here today.
>> Thank you, Brenda.
And with that, we will conclude
tonight's listening session. Uh and
thank you all very much for joining us.
We look forward to hearing from you in
the future and we appreciate your
comments and your insights tonight.
Thank you very much.